Finding Aid for Chauncey E. Spencer Papers 1914-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Chauncey E. Spencer Papers 1914-2006
Spencer, Chauncey E., 1906-
Aviator, civilian personnel officer with the U.S. Air Force; chronological and topical files, audio-visual materials, and clippings and scrapbooks.
8646 Aa/2 Ac
4.2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated in 1974 by Chauncey E. Spencer. Periodic additions were received thereafter. Donor no. 5481
The collection is open for research.
Chauncey E. Spencer was born on November 5, 1906 in Lynchburg, Virginia, the son of Anne Spencer, the poet, and Edward A. Spencer, a businessman. He graduated from Virginia Seminary and College in 1930 with a major in sociology. After a period of government employment, Spencer went to Chicago to attend aviation school. While there, he assisted in organizing a group of other like-minded individuals interested in aviation, the National Airmen's Association of America. As business manager of the organization, Spencer argued for the inclusion of African Americans in the newly formed Civilian Pilot Training Program. Spencer joined the 184th Field Artillery, Illinois National Guard in 1938, and in 1940, he volunteered to enter the Armed Forces. Instead, in October 1941, he was released from the Army in order to serve in the U.S. Air Force. Shortly thereafter the Air Force selected him to serve as a civilian employee with important responsibility for the implementation of presidential executive orders providing for the integration of the armed services. Although he met with much opposition, for his work, Spencer was award the Exceptional Civilian Service Medal in 1948.
After the war and up until his retirement in 1960, Spencer was an Air Force Civilian Personnel Employment Relations Officer at Wright-Patterson Air Force Base in Ohio. During the 1950s, based upon allegations brought against him, Spencer was suspended for period of months as a "security risk." Though completely exonerated, Spencer transferred to Norton Air Force Base in California. After leaving the Air Force, Spencer served as police commissioner of San Bernardino, California and deputy administrator of Highland Park, Michigan.
The Spencer collection has been arranged by types of materials into the following series: Biographical/autobiographical material; Chronological; Subject Files; Sound Recordings; Visual Materials; Books; and Clippings and Scrapbooks.
The Chauncey Spencer collection is an accumulation of personal materials - correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, sound and video recordings - relating to his lifelong interest in aviation, his career with the military, and the career of his mother, poetess Anne Spencer.
Subjects:
Spencer, Chauncey E. (Chauncey Edward), 1906-2002; Aeronautics.; African Americans--Michigan.; Dayton (Ohio); Discrimination in employment--United States.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Ohio--Social life and customs.; Personnel management.; United States. Army Air Forces.; World War, 1939-1945.; Wright-Patterson Air Force Base (Ohio)
Subjects - Visual Material:
African Americans.; Air pilots.; Aeronautics.; Defense industry--Ohio.; Louis, Joe, 1914-1981.; Lynchburg (Va.); Spencer, Anne, 1882-1975.; Spencer, Chauncey E. (Chauncey Edward), 1906-2002; Spencer family.; United States. Army Air Forces.; War work.; World War, 1939-1945.; Wright-Patterson Air Force Base (Ohio)
Sound Recordings
African American air pilots--History.; African Americans in aeronautics.; Spencer, Chauncey E. (Chauncey Edward), 1906-2002; Tuskegee Airmen.; United States. Air Force--African Americans.; United States. Army Air Forces. Fighter Group, 332nd.; World War, 1939-1945--Participation, African American.
Contributors: Mixed Materials
Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967.; Spencer, Anne, 1882-1975.; Spencer, Edward A., d. 1964.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Dunmore, Al.; Jefferson, Alexander.; Muse, Clarence.; Polk, Wardell.; Silvera, Frank, 1914-1970.; Spann, Ray.; Spencer, Anne, 1882-1975.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Posters.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Biographical/autobiographical material
  The Biographical/autobiographical material series consists of autobiographical reminiscences written by Spencer in 1959 and 1973, also accumulated clippings, personnel documents, two transcribed interviews, and other items containing biographical information.
  - Autobiography entitled, "It didn't just happen today." 1973 (Box 1)
  - Autobiographical reminiscences 1959 (Box 1)
  - Biographical data (Box 1)
  - Interview transcriptions (2) 1988, 2003 (Box 1)
- Chronological
  The Chronological series consists of letters and other papers from Spencer's career that have been brought together and arranged chronologically.
  - Papers 1914-2003, 16 folders (Box 1)
- Subject Files
  Subject files are those records kept by Spencer and relating to specific phases or periods in his career. Of note are files pertaining to his suit against the Ohio State News, an African American newspaper that had charged Spencer in his capacity as employee relations officer at Patterson Field with discriminating against members of his own race. This series also contains a transcript of the testimony taken in 1953 before the Security Hearing Board that resulted from the charges placed against Spencer that he was a security risk.
  - Papers concerning law suit against Ohio State News, 1945-1947, 1 folders (Box 1)
    (African American newspaper had charged that Spencer,as Employee Relations Officer at Patterson Field, had discriminated against his own race)
  - Security Hearing Board transcript, Wright-Patterson Air Force Base December 15-16, 1953 (Box 2)
  - "For White Only; A Satire of American Life" by Dr. James C. South, M.D. (Box 2)
  - History of black participation in the U.S. Military by Chauncey Spencer 1944-1945, 1949 (Box 2)
  - San Bernardino,(Calif.) County National Employ the Physically Handicapped Committee 1959 (Box 2)
  - Anne Spencer 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Black air force pilots/Tuskegee Airmen/National Air and Space Museum (Box 2)
- Sound Recordings
  The Sound Recordings date from 1970 to 1974 and consist of six cassettes. Included are a conversation with his mother, poet Anne Spencer; recordings with Al Dunmore, Alexander Jefferson, Ray Spann, Wardell Polk, and Chauncey Spencer concerning the condition of blacks in the armed forces; recording of actor-singer Clarence Muse; and a recitation (by Frank Silvera) of works of black poets.
  - Recordings of poems by James Weldon Johnson, Sterling A. Brown, and Chauncey E. Spencer recited by Frank Silvera. (Box 2)
  - Talk by Clarence Muse, actor-singer, in 1970 and interview conducted by Chauncey Spencer, 1971 (Box 2)
    [includes also Richard Nixon news conference]
  - Interview with poet, Anne Spencer by son Chauncey E. Spencer, including mention of Frederick Douglass, W.E.B. DuBois, Paul Robeson December 25, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Recording with Al Dunmore and Chauncey concerning condition of blacks in the armed forces during World War II May 29, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Recording with Al Dunmore largely concerning condition of blacks in the armed forces 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Recording with Alexander Jefferson, pilot with Tuskegee Airmen, Ray Spann, Wardell Polk, and Chauncey Spencer, discussing World War II and later activities February 5, 1974 (Box 2)
- Visual materials
  Visual Materials includes both photographs, videocassettes, and DVDs. The photographs consist of personal and family portraits and photographs reflecting his interest in aviation and his career in the military. The videotapes consist of interview with Spencer, the 50th anniversary reunion of his high school class in Virginia, and the ceremony when his mother's home was designated a historic landmark in 1976.
  - Photographs
    - Aviation
      - Civilian (Box 2)
      - Military (Box 2)
      - 1939 Tour (Box 2)
    - Dunbar High School, Lynchburg, Va. (Box 2)
    - Friends (Box 2)
    - Homes (Box 2)
    - Louis, Joe (Box 2)
    - Norton Air Force Base (Box 2)
    - Politicians (Box 2)
    - San Bernardino, Calif. (Box 2)
    - Spencer, Chauncey
      - As child and young man (Box 2)
      - Family (Box 2)
      - Portraits (Box 2)
    - Spencer, Edward, family (Box 2)
    - Wright Patterson Air Force Base (Box 2)
    - CD-ROM Images of unveiling of historical marker November 6, 2004, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 2)
  - Videotapes
    - U-matic format (Box 5)
      (color, all produced by WLVA-TV, Lynchburg, Va.)
      - Interview with Spencer, 1 videotapes U-matic (Box 5)
        (tape 1)
      - Interview with Spencer, 1 videotapes U-matic (Box 5)
        (tape 2)
      - Dunbar High School, Class of 1926 50th reunion, 1976, 1 videotapes U-matic (Box 5)
      - Anne Spencer home becomes historic landmark 1976, 1 videotapes U-matic (Box 5)
    - VHS format
      - "An evening with Chauncey E. Spencer," February 8, 1996 Smithsonian National Air and Space Museum, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) 90 minutes (Box 5)
      - "A Place in the Sky" (being the Chauncey Spencer Story), 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
      - Aircraft Crash File (United States Air Force) 1943-1944, 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
      - "The Flying Fortress", 1 videotapes VHS (TM) 20 minutes (Box 5)
      - "The 18th Air Force", 1 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 5)
  - DVDs
    - Chauncey Spencer in his home describing framed photographs on wall and relating the images to the events in his life, particularly African American airmen; portion of CS funeral service; interlude without commentary of Spencer photographs; "The 99th Pursuit Squadron", 1 optical disks DVDs ca. 30 min. (Box 5)
    - Talk by CS on his career, 1 optical disks DVDs 88 minutes (Box 5)
- Books
  The Books series consists of monographs on African Americans in the armed forces, a volume about his mother Anne Spencer.
  - Breakthrough on the Color Front by Lee Nichols, concerning the integration of the U.S. armed forces (Box 3)
  - Lonely Eagles concerning black air force pilots (Box 3)
  - Time's Unfolding Garden concerning Anne Spencer (Box 3)
  - Who is Chauncey Spencer by Chauncey E. Spencer (1975), 2 copies (Box 3)
- Clippings and scrapbooks
  The Clippings and Scrapbooks series consists of three scrapbooks that Spencer had put together from his career. Included with clippings are photographs and personal memorabilia. One volume concerns his family life and his interest aviation; another dates from the period when Spencer was at the Fairfield Air Depot in Ohio. This volume includes many photographs of the work and activities of the civilian personnel at that air force base.
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and articles 1929-1973, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - New York Sunday News, September 4,1949 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous newspapers and magazines, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook concerning role of blacks at the Air Material Command 1942-1949 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous newspapers (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook concerning the work of civilian personnel at the Fairfield Air Depot (Patterson Field, Dayton, Ohio) 1943, undated
    (this scrapbook has been taken apart for preservation reasons, and the contents arranged by topic)
    - General (Box 3)
    - Photographs
      - Award ceremonies (Box 3)
      - Civilian barracks (Box 3)
      - Employees, Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Factory work
        - Airplanes and engines (Box 3)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Office work (Box 3)
      - Outside work (Box 3)
      - Parking lots (Box 3)
      - Recreation (Box 3)
      - Skyway Park Dormitories (Box 3)
      - War Chest drive (Box 3)
      - Warehouse work (Box 3)
      - Welfare Office and Blood drive (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Outsize posters (Folder Ac)
  - Scrapbook circa 1925-1965 (Box 4)
    (Includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, photographs, and personal memorabilia largely concerning family life and interest in aviation; also photographs of Joe Louis during World War II.)